So I wanted to
discuss concurrency with you.
And this on concrete examples, for
example this example from the slides.
For this, I had already claimed that
t2 and t3 were activated concurrently here.
Of course, we can first consider that
t2 and t3 are each activated by itself.
And that's pretty obvious, because for instance t2 has
as a precondition only this one token of s2.
And that one is present.
So t2 could fire and then
put a token here in s4.
And in the same way, it's also the case
that t3 has only one precondition, which is
that it requires only one token from s3.
There is one token there.
So t3 could fire and put a token in s4.
And that would be the next situation.
That would be the fireability
of t2 and t3 individually.
However, we can intuitively see that t2
and t3 could in principle
fire at the same time.
Because these two
preconditions do not overlap.
They have nothing to do with each other.
So, what I had just
done with the two individual tokens,
I could intuitively do in parallel.
I could also say:
The two tokens could move to t2
and t3 respectively at the same time,
so to speak, to satisfy the respective precondition,
and then t2 and t3 could also fire simultaneously.
Because they operate on completely different
tokens, since there is no overlap.
So that we can say:
Then t2 and t3 can also both
fire and just lead to this situation.
That's the idea of parallelism and
concurrency, that t2 and t3 could both
fulfill their precondition in the
marking that we saw, and they
could do so without
interfering with each other.
And that's what also the formal
condition (which was on the slide),
ultimately expressed by this sum
and comparison with the current marking.
For the concrete constellation,
that was the case.
Of course, if the Petri net is
different or the interconnections of the transitions
are different, it
can look quite different.
So if we had about this same example,
but had another arrow (so
still an additional dependency), we say
about here another arrow (which is then of
course an additional precondition) from s3 to t2.
This would mean that there are now two
precondition places for t2, namely s2 and s3.
What would then be valid here?
It would still hold
that t2 and t3 are of
course each fireable on their own.
So t3 anyway.
This t3 has a precondition.
The token is there, so t3 could fire.
But also t2 can fire.
Because what does t2 expect?
This t2 expects that there is
a token on both precondition places.
And this is the case.
That is, t2 could also fire
and put a token on s4.
However, t2 and t3 cannot fire
simultaneously as in the previous example.
Because in order for t2 to fire,
it would take out these two tokens.
And then t3 cannot fire
simultaneously, or in parallel, or concurrently.
Because t3 then finds nothing here,
no token that could be used.
Therefore, in this constellation, this new
specification of preconditions (in particular, that t2
has this second precondition, which depends
on S3), it would not be
possible that simply both transitions
t2 and t3 are activated concurrently.
Although they are
each activated separately.
For example, if we were to make another
change here, namely to have it so that there
are two tokens on s3 of
our marking, then it would again be
true that t2 is activated, t3 is activated,
and even t2 and t3 are also activated concurrently.
In the situation, it would be
again that we could of course fire
t2 and t3 concurrent/parallel.
Because then t2 would be able to take
this token and one of the two tokens from
down here to be activated, and
t3 could take the other token.
Then again, we would have the situation
where we could have basically done it
in parallel: that is, t2 and t3
could fire without interfering with each other.
But that was only because I
had provided two tokens down here.
Because then the preconditions of t2
and t3 can be fulfilled simultaneously.
So it depends exactly on the
particular precondition and which tokens are present.
Let's look at another
example, first this one.
What is activated concurrently here?
Now this is very simple, this example.
We can see factually right away that
probably all three transitions are activated here.
And this is concurrent in the sense that
we have exactly three tokens at the top
and exactly any one of them could
make one of the three transitions happy.
Or that we could go something like
this, and then of course t1, t2,
t3 could be executed in parallel (and
each occupy one place, their postcondition place).
That would be our first example,
where we have a three-element concurrent set.
On the slide also appeared:
Not only can we have
two transitions concurrent, but about here
the T' set of concurrently
activated transitions would simply be the
entire transition set, namely t1, t2, t3.
That's possible, and in that
case that's exactly how it occurs.
And we can calculate that it
also satisfies the formal condition for
concurrency of all three transitions.
However, this was also only the case
because we had the three tokens above.
If we take a similar constellation, but
with only two tokens above, then what holds?
Again, t1, t2, t3
are each activated separately.
Because each one requests only one token
from s1, and there are even two.
So no problem, we could
fire each one of these transitions.
We could also fire two
of them at the same time.
I'm not allowed to
duplicate anything, of course.
So when I take the token
out, it really has to go.
So it could be
that we decide, for example, to
consider t1 and t2 as concurrently activated.
They are concurrently activated because
there are actually enough tokens.
The same would be true for
t1, t3 and for t2, t3.
However, not for t1, t2, and t3 together.
So the concrete marking that we
have here, with only two tokens at
the top, ensures that the quantity t1, t2 and
the quantity t2, t3 and the quantity t1 t3 are
each activated concurrently, but the total
quantity t1, t2, t3 is not.
Because the two tokens above are not enough to
have all three transitions fireable at the same time.
We can calculate this
again on the slides.
Then we have this example.
It's a little bit more interesting,
because there are more cross dependencies.
Especially at this point, of course.
What is valid here?
First of all, t1, t2, t3
are certainly not all three concurrently activated.
But there are
concurrent activations here.
For example, t1 and
t3 are concurrently activated.
Because we can satisfy, say,
t1 by taking these two tokens,
and completely independently, t3
could take this token.
And then actually here again a parallel
passage through t1 and t3 would be possible.
This t2 would not be affected
by this, and could also not
act, because t2 would require that
there is still a token here.
But this is not the case.
This would be the case for t1, t3.
And analogously, we could have considered
that t2, t3 are activated here concurrently.
Because these two tokens would be able
to go to t2, and completely independently t3
would be able to consume this token, and thus
just t2, t3 would be able to fire concurrently.
However, not t1 and t2.
This fails because we would need on the one hand
that for t1 and on the other hand that for t2.
Exactly the marked center
would be needed twice.
This is not possible here.
The token can't go here
and here at the same time.
And then also t1, t2,
t3 cannot be activated concurrently.
Because then also every subset of
it would have to be activated concurrently.
And t1, t2 already isn't.
Of course, we can fix that
again, but only by changing the marking.
So if we would consider the case
that here exactly on this problematic place there
are two tokens, then indeed again
all three transitions are activated concurrently.
Then these two tokens could be
used to activate t1, and at
the same time without overlap these
two tokens could be used to
activate t2, and anyway completely independently
t3 could operate on this one token.
Here it would indeed be possible to say:
The token moves here, the token moves
there, the token moves here, the token
moves there, the token moves here.
Then t1, t2,
t3 are activated concurrently.
Which means that
actually now potentially any
order of firing would be possible.
So when we write down firing sequences, we
don't write down t1, t2, t3 in parallel,
but we could say: t1, t2,
t3 are activated concurrently and can
then be fired in
any permutation, so to speak.
Possible firing sequences here now
would be t1, t2, t3 or
t1, t3, t2 or t2, t1, t3; t2,
t3, t1; t3, t1, t2 or t3, t2, t1.
This is a general observation
regarding this notion of concurrent activation.
That if we have concurrently
activated transitions, then any firing
sequence of them is possible.
Because they simply
don't affect each other.